Ralph E. Wadleigh Photograph Collection
© 2005 University of Connecticut
Ralph E. Wadleigh Photograph Collection.
undated, 1886-1965
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Center.
Wadleigh, Ralph E.
.25 linear feet.
Ralph E. Wadleigh was a railroad enthusiast in New London, Connecticut.
MSS20020002
Biography
Ralph E. Wadleigh was a resident of New London, Connecticut.
Scope and Content
The collection consists of 42 photographs of railroad locomotives and scenes related to the Monadnock Northern, the New Haven Railroad, Grand Trunk Railroad, and the Central Vermont Railroad.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of New England railroad history materials. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Index Terms
This record series is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Subjects:
New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad.; Monadnock Northern Railroad.; Grand Trunk Railroad.; Central Vermont Railroad.; Railroads-Connecticut-Photographs.; Railroads-Massachusetts-Photographs.; Railroads-Rhode Island-Photographs.; Locomotives.; Photography—Connecticut Railroads.; Photographs.
Document Types:
Photographs.
Restrictions on Access
There are no access restrictions on this collection.
Acquisition Information
Materials were donated by Ralph E. Wadleigh, Jr., of Reading, Massachusetts.
Detailed Description
- Series I: Collection, undated, 1886-1965
  - Train consist with Monadnock Northern locomotive, undated (Other 2002-0002.ph1)
    3.5×3.5 inches, B&W. Photograph of two boxcars, one locomotive with tender, and two passenger cars, at what appears to be a station. Equipment could be in a dead line. Electrical poles on right.
  - Train consist with Monadnock Northern locomotive, undated (Other 2002-0002.ph2)
    3.5×3.5 inches, B&W. Monadnock Northern locomotive 15 parked in front of a building. Partial view of boxcar and passenger car visible. Tracks in foreground.
  - Train ticket booth, undated (Other 2002-0002.ph3)
    3.5×3.5 inches, B&W. Small ticket booth with signs atop reading “Ride Steam trains of Yesteryear” and “Keene.” Automobile parking lot in foreground, steam train behind booth. Three people standing at booth.
  - Monadnock Mountain locomotive 15, undated (Other 2002-0002.ph4)
    3.5×3.5 inches, B&W. Monadnock Northern locomotive 15 parked in front of a building Partial view of boxcar and passenger car visible. Tracks in foreground.
  - Monadnock Mountain locomotive 15, 1964? (Other 2002-0002.ph5)
    3.5×3.5 inches, B&W. Rear right-side view of Monadnock Northern locomotive 15. Partial view of passenger car with the words “....aineer air conditioned” on the side. 12 men and women, and 1 child standing or sitting on ground in front of train (none posed).
  - Steam locomotive, undated (Other 2002-0002.ph6)
    3.5×3.5 inches, B&W. Nearly head-on view of steam locomotive, tracks in foreground. Possibly Monadnock Northern locomotive 15. Location is fields and hills, house in far background.
  - Monadnock Northern locomotive 15, undated (Other 2002-0002.ph7)
    3.5×3.5 inches, B&W. Right side three-quarter view of Monadnock Northern steam locomotive 15 with at least five passenger cars in its consist. Many (more than 50) people standing next to train. Railroad employee leaning out of cab window.
  - Grand Trunk locomotive 3411, 1955 August (Other 2002-0002.ph8)
    3.5×3.5 inches, B&W. Rear right-side view of Grand Trunk Railroad locomotive 3411. Railroad employee leaning out of cab window. On back of photograph: “South Paris Maine Station Portland to Montreal.”
  - Grand Trunk locomotive 2576, 1952 August 28 (Other 2002-0002.ph9)
    3.5″×3.5″, B&W. Right side view of Grand Trunk locomotive 2576. Partial view of boxcars in front and in back of locomotive. Man standing next to engine, near cab.
  - Grand Trunk Railroad train, 1952 August 28 (Other 2002-0002.ph10)
    3.5″×3.5″, B&W. Long consist of Grand Trunk Railroad train with at least three boxcars in front of the locomotive (probably 2576). Two men standing at cab, two men standing next to train
  - Last steam train Union Station, New London, CT, 1952 September 30 (Other 2002-0002.ph11)
    3.5″×3.5″, B&W. 4.5″×3″, B&W. Right-side three quarter view of Grand Trunk Railroad locomotive 463 with two passenger cars. Man leaning from cab window, one man standing next to tender. On back of photo: “Last steam train Union Station New London, CT Sept 30, 1953.”
  - C.V. 314 - 6th St. East New London, ca. 1910 (Other 2002-0002.ph12)
    3.5″×3.5″, B&W. Right-side view of Central Vermont locomotive 314. Four men posed standing on the locomotive, four men posed standing in front of locomotive. Partial view of Gold Star Memorial Bridge and tops of houses in background.
  - C.V. #317 Yard Switcher at East New London, ca. 1909 (Other 2002-0002.ph13)
    4.75″×3.5″, B&W. Right-side three-quarter view of Central Vermont steam locomotive 317. Man looking out cab window.
  - Central Vermont #103 near Thames Shipyard. Engineer believed to be George Alger, ca. 1908-1910 (Other 2002-0002.ph14)
    3.5″×5″, B&W. Right-side three-quarter view of Central Vermont locomotive 103 with boxcar. Possibly steam coming from smokebox. Man, identified as possibly engineer George Alger, leaning out of cab window.
  - Central Vermont RR wrecker at New London, CT, undated (Other 2002-0002.ph15)
    3.5″×6″, B&W. Central Vermont Railroad wrecker in New London rail yard, under Gold Star Memorial Bridge. Partial view of unidentified boxcars in background.
  - Locomotive 6218, 1965 September (Other 2002-0002.ph16)
    3.5″×5″, B&W. Right side three-quarter view of a 4-8-0 locomotive #6218. Unidentified railroad, possibly a Canadian National Railroad train or Boston and Maine Railroad. People standing next to locomotive. Possibly located in Brattleboro, Vermont.
  - Taken in the Notch Amherst-Holyoke Line about 1932. Motorman: Bates, 1932 (Other 2002-0002.ph17)
    3.5″×5″, B&W. Front right side three-quarter view of a trolley, Holyoke line. Motorman (identified as “Bates”) standing in doorway, looking at camera.
  - Taken at Taftville [postcard], 1907 (Other 2002-0002.ph18)
    3.5″×5.5″, B&W. Front view of locomotive 1657 with five young men sitting on or standing next to the pilot.
  - Locomotive 364 with Men Posed on Pilot [postcard], 1907(?) (Other 2002-0002.ph19)
    3.5″×5″, B&W. Front view of locomotive 364, unidentified railroad. Smoke coming from smokestack. Five men posed standing on pilot.
  - Taftville Tunnel North End, 1907 (Other 2002-0002.ph20)
    3.5″×5″, B&W. Locomotive 364, unidentified railroad, emerging from Taftville tunnel. One man leaning out from cab window. On back of photo: working in Taftville Tunnel 1907 North end.
  - Working in Taftville Tunnel South End [postcard], 1907 (Other 2002-0002.ph21)
    3.5″×5″, B&W. Steam locomotive 364, unidentified railroad, emerging from train tunnel. Man leaning out of cab window.
  - At Taftville 1907 [postcard], 1907 (Other 2002-0002.ph22)
    3.5″×5.25″, B&W. Right-side three-quarter view of steam locomotive 312 (unknown railroad) with box or hopper cars. Four men sitting on track next to train.
  - New Haven 2-8-0 at Saybrook, Connecticut, 1895 (Other 2002-0002.ph23)
    3.5″×4.5″, B&W. On back: “New Haven “Hogs” (2-8-0) double heading a caboose to break through main line snowdrifts arrives at Saybrook Jct. Winter of 1895. Last of these engines (200 class) were scrapped about 1926.” 7 men stand with engine.
  - New Haven 2-8-0 at Saybrook, Connecticut, 1895 (Other 2002-0002.ph23)
  - Train wreck, Wood River Junction, 1895 (Other 2002-0002.ph24)
    3.5″×5″, B&W. On back: Cleaning up wreck on the old “Stonington Division” New Haven Road - At Wood River Junction, R.I..” Crane removing debris from wreck, many men standing at scene.
  - Locomotives submerged in floodwaters, Norwich, Connecticut [postcard], 1886 February (Other 2002-0002.ph25)
    3.5″×5.5″, B&W. On back: “Lined up at Norwich Conn to be moved away from flood Feb 1886 but water overtook them at Norwich Conn. First engine no. 12 “Sacham” 2nd no. 14 “Shetucket” Engine in house no. 16 “Tigu[?]” ” Locos on destroyed tracks.
  - Wrecked train with boiler exposed, ca. 1890s (Other 2002-0002.ph26)
    3.25″×4.5, B&W. Unidentified damaged train with boilers exposed. Many men standing near train, looking at camera.
  - Train coach interior, 1895 (Other 2002-0002.ph27)
    3.5″×3.75″, B&W. On back: “Interior of snowbound local coach, 1895. Conductor W.J. Manwaring (standing in aisle) still living. Went railroading in 1878”. Seven men standing or seated in a passenger coach. Lamps (possibly gas) visible from ceiling.
  - Snowbound New Haven Railroad locomotive, Derby Junction, Connecticut, 1895 (Other 2002-0002.ph28)
    3.5″×3.75, B&W. On back: Saybrook - Waterbury local snowbound at Derby Jct. (Devon) winter 1895. Engineer is shovelling snow into tank to make water.” Rear left-side three-quarter view of New Haven Railroad locomotive, men standing in front with shovels.
  - New Haven Railroad steam locomotive 388 in Southbridge, Massachusetts [postcard], 1935 March 27 (Other 2002-0002.ph29)
    3.5″×5.5″, B&W. On back: “New Haven 388 Southbridge, Mass 3/27/35 Fireman: Harvey Tourtellotte.” Left side view of New Haven steam locomotive 388, smoke coming from smokebox, engineer leaning out of cab window.
  - “Firing Up” at Willimantic, undated (Other 2002-0002.ph30)
    3.0″×4.5″, B&W. Front view of unidentified steam locomotive with long consist of passenger trains, dark smoke coming from smoke box. Many people clustered around train.
  - New Haven Railroad at New London, CT, undated (Other 2002-0002.ph31)
    2.5″×4″, B&W. Right-side three-quarter view of unidentified steam locomotive pulling into a train station. View of platform. Water tank in background.
  - Engine 1388 and train leave Cedar Hill Yard, undated (Other 2002-0002.ph32)
    3.25″×4.5″, B&W. Left-side three-quarter view of New Haven Railroad steam locomotive 1388 with long train of passenger cars, coming around a curve. Steam coming from smokebox.
  - Engine 1388 at Cedar Hill, undated (Other 2002-0002.ph33)
    3.0″×4.5″, B&W. Right-side three-quarter view (from above) of New Haven Railroad steam locomotive 1388, smoke coming from smokebox. Automobiles and electrical poles in the background.
  - Last steam train, Engine 1372 South Station, Boston, 1952 April 27 (Other 2002-0002.ph34)
    3.0″×4.5″, B&W. New Haven Railroad steam locomotive 1372, with passenger cars, in South Station, Boston, Massachusetts. People standing next to engine, one boy standing on engine near cab. Signal bridge above engine.
  - Engines 1388 and 1372, Last Steamers, leaving South Station, Boston, 1952 April 27 (Other 2002-0002.ph35)
    3.0″×4.5″, B&W. Front view of New Haven Railroad steam locomotives 1388 and 1372, in railroad station. Several men on platform between trains. Signal bridge above engines.
  - Putnam, Westbound Train, Boston-Waterbury passes last steam train, 1952 April 27 (Other 2002-0002.ph36)
    3.0″×4.5″, B&W. Right side three quarter view of New Haven Railroad steam engine 1372, on tracks next to a diesel passenger train in Putnam, Connecticut.
  - Last steamer and Eastbound Waterbury-Boston Train, Meet at Putnam, 1952 April 27 (Other 2002-0002.ph37)
    3.0″×4.5″, B&W. Three-quarter side view of two engines facing other on track in Putnam, Connecticut. Includes New Haven Railroad steam locomotive 1372 and an unidentified passenger train. Over two dozen people gathered around trains.
  - Last Steam Train New Haven RR New London, Conn. Engine 1372, 1952 April 27 (Other 2002-0002.ph38)
    3.0″×4.5″, B&W. Left -side three-quarter view of New Haven Railroad steam locomotive 1372, with passenger cars. Dark smoke billowing from smoke-stack. Men standing near train. Baggage trucks on side.
  - Last steam train at Putnam, Conn., 1952 April 27 (Other 2002-0002.ph39)
    3.0″×4.5″, B&W. Right-side three quarter view of New Haven Railroad steam locomotive 1372, with 7 passenger cars. People gathered near engine.
  - Last steam train, New London, Conn., 1952 April 27 (Other 2002-0002.ph40)
    3.0″×4.5″, B&W. Right-side three-quarter view of New Haven Railroad steam locomotive 1372, at New London, Connecticut, railroad station. Platform visible on side. Overhead walkway above engine.
  - At New London, CT, 1953 September (Other 2002-0002.ph41)
    3.0″×5.0″, B&W. Rear view of unidentified train. Five men standing on caboose platform, three men standing next to train.
  - 7:03 AM for Boston, 1953 May (Other 2002-0002.ph42)
    3.5″×6.0, B&W. Left-side view of New Haven Railroad electric locomotives on raised embankment with other tracks in foreground. Note on back: Thames River Bridge at New London in distance.